Guide to the Eugène and Maria Jolas Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Eugène Jolas - Writings, 1879-1971; Series II; 6.75; (16 boxes)
  - BOOKS OF POEMS
    - Hypnolog des Scheitelauges
      - Printed version, 1932 (Box 15, Folder 280)
    - I Have Seen Monsters and Angels
      - Scrapbook, 1939 (Box 15, Folder 281)
    - The Language of Night
      - Printed version, 1932 (Box 15, Folder 282)
    - Lorraine Poem
      - Requiem for my Mother Lettre Requiem for my Father/Dirge for a Borderman To my Three Brothers on the Maginot Line Remembering the Lorraine Madonna (Box 15, Folder 283)
      - Frontier Reveries
        My Brother
        Angelus
        The Guard
        Border Evening
        Grape-Time
        At Watch
        Film
        The Poet
        Autumn
      - Danse Macabre
        Revolution
        Nocturne
        Chaos
        Silhouettes
        Decay
        Postwar
        Summer Chant
        Interlude
        Metamorphosis
        The End
      - Words for a Jewish Woman The Frontierless Night/Address to the Strasbourg Friends
      - "My words were suddenly astride..." "The beautiful bar maid..." "I remember the leaves..." "the blond world crumbled..." "My mother fled today..."
      - "We played in the ancient ruins..." "i remember the lonely town..." "in the freed capital..." "trancelimned caresses..." "the scarlet harp smiles..." "once there were giant trees..."
      - List of titles
    - Mots-Déluge
      - Advertisement, 1933, 1941 (Box 15, Folder 284)
      - Scrapbook
        See: Books - Vertigral - scrapbook
    - Planets and Angels
      - Printed version, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 285)
    - Poems about Stars and Planets
      - Cloud Sidereal (Box 15, Folder 286)
        "My wings flutter..."
        "O loneliness of million suns..."
      - Sidereal
        "When I was young..."
      - Vertical-Sidereal
        "You were with me always..."
      - Sidereal-Vertical
        "All the shimmer planets were..."
        "Always you were with me..."
        "I conjure the wingman out of my..."
        "Moon,moon.Ascending gleam..."
      - Vertical
        "Fireglint in the cloud..."
        "Snowhite blossomcandles blazed..."
        "What is the vacuous hour..."
        "In the war night we listened..."
        "In the blackout we listened..."
        "In the hour of the tomb..."
        "The skyship travelled..."
        "We said you are the woman..."
        "You are the woman Sfeira..."
        "We were in the shimmer orbit..."
        "We were in the titanic crystal..."
      - In Ascensions Astronomicas
        "Up we go to the wild blue..."
        "Armies of the sun..."
        "Poem fragments: birdwing..."
        "Our sidereal odyssee..."
        "Angels Lumor
        "Lumor said the golden..."
        "Vertical:La fin du monde..."
        "Vertical:Denis l'Aréopagite..."
        "Vertical:Journey..."
        "Angelic Revolution:Rain wind..."
        "Messengers of the rosa basilica..."
        "We were sidereal vagabonds..."
        "Seraphos flittered in the silken..."
        "All afternoon the wind moaned..."
        "Seraphos saw the great tanks..."
        "Seraphic longing..."
        "Two lovers stood on the alpine..."
        "In the brumous evening..."
        "The sun rutilated..."
        "Pneuma left Lumina..."
        "Arcturus Mars..."
        "Glasslightringing silence..."
        "The flaccid afternoon..."
        "Up we trailed..."
        "You said let us leave the cavern..."
        "The anguish of the earth..."
        "Crystal chantworld..."
        "The sleepgrey hours glided..."
        "Our sidereal odysee..."
        "Now the weltangst rumbles..."
        "whipflail of poison rain..."
        "The hideous fumepall..."
        "We were in the shimmerorbit..."
        "Cliff crystal houses..."
        "We were in the vast..."
        "Fireglint in the cloud mountains..."
        "We were sleeping..."
        "All the planetoids..."
        "We flished through..."
        "We stood in the ancient..."
        "We conjured the wingmen..."
        "We were asleep..."
        "The mountain village..."
        "In the fire of the twilight..."
        "the seraphic longing..."
        "The roserain..."
        "We stand am Meer und lanshte..."
        "Epilogue/We rise higher..."
        "Angelic Flight/Nous eveillions..."
    - Poésie de mots inconnus
      - Advertisement, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 287)
    - Reporters
      - Master List (Box 15, Folder 288)
      - Section A (Box 15, Folder 289)
        "Always there gleamed..."
        "We came from Europe's malady..."
        "In the tenement-street..."
        "This is the world..."
        "The afternoon sickered down..."
        "My words hid..."
        "Manhattan Courier..."
        "The newsmen blisterhue..."
        "We were on a voyage..."
        "Le parc attend..."
        "It overwhelms them..."
        "Machine-words whinehooted..."
        "The immutable bagatelles..."
        "He remembered gulls..."
        "A slow music..."
        "He looked through..."
        "All the grammar..."
        "Whirwaves clutter..."
        "The world is afraid..."
        "This is the golden..."
        "What did the newsman..."
        "He said I remember..."
        "Geysers de sang..."
        "A worker wept..."
        "And nobody understands..."
        "He says oh immigrants..."
        "En face des chimères..."
        "Icily blew the wind..."
        "All night long the wind cried..."
        "We were in the delirium..."
        "And he thought..."
        "The rhymes lose their shimmer..."
        "Metallic incantations..."
        "Music died in a lucid prophecy..."
        "The world fell into the eyes..."
        "A wind-bloar came swishing..."
        "Hako venoome vovoe..."
        "And now the quiet lamp burns..."
        "I saw the chimerical America..."
        "And guatemala silvers in fear..."
        "The horizontal world is dying..."
        "Incendiary thoroughfares..."
        "The make-up man tells a story..."
        "What a twinklevertigo..."
        "We saw the mill-town..."
        "Do you hear those lynotypists..."
        "SS Titanic hits iceberg..."
        "He remembers the mill-town..."
        "The builders of the city..."
        "Hey babimno..."
        "Did you glyph those mugs..."
        "The newswreckers grey..."
        "In the night the city-room..."
        "All day all night..."
        "The signs of the archaic..."
      - Section B (Box 15, Folder 290)
        "Once more we are..."
        "Manhattan courier..."
        "The city is asleep..."
        "The swoop towards the nickel..."
        "une misère envahit..."
        "Sunflooded port in south..."
        "The newsman chanted..."
        "London news-sheet..."
        "l'exode vers l'ouest..."
        "A slow music illumines..."
        "It was night in the alien..."
        "Ici le poste WYOP..."
        "The newsman shudders..."
        "the world is afraid..."
        "maintenant tous les chemins..."
        "In balooshima mountains music..."
        "What did the newsman hear..."
        "He said I remember Manhattan..."
        "donde estan las estrellas..."
        "il reve la nouvelle langue..."
        "He says Oh immigrants..."
        "En face des chimères
        "In Europe there gleamed..."
        "He wanders alone..."
        "City of metamorphoses..."
        "And the beasts break..."
        "Will Rockefeller Center..."
        "Et tous les mythes..."
        "Je vous salue inconnus..."
        "We are the indrunk welders..."
        "Nous sommes les nomades..."
        "garden aint nothing..."
        "He remembers the milltown..."
        "We airwaved flunties..."
        "Enter verticalism..."
        "Cosmopolis brule..."
        "tree of life grew spring..."
        "The cortex of the age..."
        "We remembered the steel-city..."
        "In the night..."
        "Joseph Pulitzer..."
        "Les ombres se faulilent..."
        "All day all night we hear..."
      - Section C - REPORTER POEME-MIGRATIONS (Box 15, Folder 291)
        "Preface/We are the wordmen..."
        "He remembered straddling..."
        "He said where are the friends..."
        "My words grew into hymns..."
        "He remembered the boat..."
        "My words amerigrated..."
        "The land was waiting for snow..."
        "Nights in mill-towns..."
        "His words carnival..."
        "Unfettered in his nomad..."
        "My words hid in the coil..."
        "He thought of all the wanderers..."
        "The fairy tale words..."
        "He knew they were slaves..."
        "I walked across..."
        "Millions merged into oneness..."
        "Endless return..."
        "Solitude was filled..."
        "We were racing along..."
        "The burghers yawned..."
        "We were alone in the mill-town..."
        "Dialogue bluster smoked..."
        "I dreamed I wanted..."
        "The trains passed..."
        "Summernight fell..."
        "The summer evening..."
        "The litany of names..."
        "The words ghosted..."
        "I wandered through..."
        "It was night when..."
        "I watched the Mississipi..."
        "The motor roadwhirred..."
        "In Europe there..."
        "All night long..."
        "The chaos of my despair..."
        "I stood in the tangled..."
        "The hours were blessed..."
        "Wonderful was the auction..."
        "The French words sang..."
        "We were romantic voyagers..."
        "My words were at war..."
        "My heart was held by the waves..."
        "The forgotten sage came..."
        "My America-words turned inward..."
        "The almanach of the white men..."
        "The men with the third eye..."
        "In New Orleans we migrated..."
        "We plunged into the lexicon..."
        "I owned everything..."
        "We invented the wind..."
        "My words were suddenly astride..."
        "My father-words came back..."
        "Oh it was spring once more..."
        "I heard the wind..."
        "Often I could not forget..."
        "My words went in search..."
      - Section D (Box 15, Folder 292)
        "My mother-words went..."
        "The bell had words of silk..."
        "The ancient wound..."
        "Fume-sheets of three rivers..."
        "I walked across a bridge..."
        "Endless return in the..."
        "All the grammar lay..."
        "The little town stood missing..."
        "I said where are the crosses..."
      - Section E (Box 15, Folder 293)
        "Rain whips the fetid streets..."
        "Les mots tressaillent..."
        "The night has lost its elegies..."
        "Darkly menaced..."
        "L'asile de l'amour..."
        "Nuit nebuleuse de metal..."
        "Toutes les ondes ont perdu..."
        "La misère des masques s'abat..."
        "Et c'est de nouveau la guerre..."
        "The flatterers of the human..."
        "All the mergenthalers mourn..."
        "The welcome..."
        "The earth begins to rumble..."
        "What twinklevertigo..."
        "A dead man walks..."
        "Many telephones shringle..."
        "Men wandered to Shinar..."
        "Elsangre y los Besos..."
        "They counted the white..."
        "We were always building Babel..."
        "A malady of panic shook..."
      - Section F - Between the Maginot and Siegfried Line (Box 15, Folder 294)
        "What was it that..."
        "Here I had landed..."
        "The engineers were hammering..."
        "The paradise-age of childhood..."
        "What was the voice that called..."
      - Section G - Men Waiting For War (Box 15, Folder 295)
        "Nobody passed down the street..."
        "My old-world town sighed..."
        "The air of the border-town..."
        "The solitary hour was sick..."
        "He remembered in the cavernous..."
        "The deep-forest caressed..."
        "One of these nights..."
      - Section H (Box 15, Folder 296)
        "Alone I wander through..."
        "My mother-words went to..."
        "The machines will go into ruin..."
        "The newsman chanted to himself..."
        "In walking through..."
        "It was night in the alien city..."
        "He wanders alone through the night..."
        "We are the inkdrunk welders..."
      - Section I - Manhattan Reporter (Box 15, Folder 297)
        "Nous sommes les reveurs..."
        "We were immersed..."
        "We remember the gravity..."
        "We thought of the name Havas..."
        "They came in from their..."
        "We were in a glitzermood..."
        "Nochedarkling music moans..."
        "Wenn ich an New York..."
        "Schwermuetige lieder weinten..."
        "Im fernen Lande hoerte ich..."
        "In den einsamen Stunden..."
        "Ich suchte im Wildgestruepp..."
        "The new language came..."
        "In the elevated train..."
        "Going to work before dawn..."
        "The west was flaming..."
        "A slow music illuminated..."
        "I wandered through the East..."
        "The machine did not remember..."
        "Le temps restait toujours..."
        "we came through the crashgates..."
        "Habitacles grouillants..."
        "ahora I hear the metalboom..."
        "the foretaling of the myth..."
        "the chromatic scale held..."
        "I remember Manhattan..."
        "We were memory-sick wanderers..."
        "We saw blizzards..."
        "For we wanted to go into..."
        "The city was asleep..."
        "The gravity of the city..."
        "We were the planet-reaching..."
        "Salud to the celestial towers..."
        "I remember the girl..."
        "We lived in the vertical..."
        "Mes mots s'en allaient..."
        "Nightern clung to summer..."
        "Nous serons les hommes..."
        "Nous sommes ivres de mots..."
        "And look at Menneskeheden..."
        "I remember the dream that often..."
      - Section J - News from Germany (Box 15, Folder 298)
        "Prologue - The rains flee over..."
        "A broken piano moaned..."
        "We worked in the captured..."
        "Nous étions fatigués..."
        "We watched the artillery..."
        "We meditated Charlemagne's..."
        "The lobster shift creaks..."
        "Nous avons marché..."
        "That day we saw violets..."
        "The rockets went off..."
        "The bleak winter hours creaked..."
        "We were tired and the wire..."
        "Metallic incantations glided..."
        "I wandered amid..."
        "What were these words..."
        "We vegetated in the dead city..."
        "Spring gleamed over the..."
        "Oh deep symbol of time..."
        "Old Hollands the printer..."
        "I said what are these sounds..."
        "Bud Sockolsky the GI scribbled..."
        "The cortex of the age broke..."
      - Section K - Preface to News from Germany (Box 16, Folder 299)
        "We were the newsmen..."
        "We watched the shillervista..."
        "All the words from many continents..."
        "We came from the city rooms..."
        "Les prisonniers francais..."
        "We were again reporters..."
        "der dunklen erinnerungen..."
        "Incendiary thoroughfare..."
        "The shell-harried factory town..."
        "Bunni crint tongara millting..."
        "Sending DIR..." DIM..." zhg vvvvv..."
        "Titatic birds flutter..."
        "A blindbloar came swishing..."
        "Nearby brummed the bark..."
        "Lange lief traumschliefen wir..."
        "A new language came with..."
        "And a great terror seized us..."
      - Section L - Souvenir of the Rhine (Box 16, Folder 300)
        Prologue: Euramerican Chant in Wartime
        The Liberation of France
        The Aachen Hours
        Anguish Thoughts in Dueren
        Exorcist Interludes in Marburg
        The Rhine (Mainz to Oppenheim)
        The Babel Hour of the Reporters
        German Poems in Tuebingen
        Malor's Verbs in Berlin
        News Phantasmata in Wiesbaden
        Lobstershift in Munich
        Night Thoughts in Frankfurt/ (including Korea)
        My Guardian Angel
        Multilingual Epilogue
        Souvenirs
        "I lived in Germany at the turn..."
        "I heard the German children..."
        "That spring we saw the nomads..."
        "The wire room echoed gliss..."
        "I am weary of this St.Vitus..."
        "The words you use are bestained..."
        "Comrades do you remember..."
      - Section M - Preface (Box 16, Folder 301)
        "He walked through the abyssal..."
        "Once more he roved through..."
        "His memory walked again..."
        "I said I am alone in the heart..."
        "The cyclopean whorl rose into..."
      - Section N - Preface
        "We are always sailing..."
        "The Atlantic ache was always..."
        "They saw in our dreams..."
        "The way I was in the gutterdays..."
      - Section O (Box 16, Folder 302)
        "The story had no meaning..."
        "We were rent in the travailing..."
        "our words carnival-played..."
        "We marched through..."
        "The torrid heat sickered down..."
        "The aliens in the thunderstreets..."
        "We were drunken with the masses..."
        "We thought of all the wanderers..."
        "The syllables of the new language..."
        "Wandering through the downtown..."
      - Section P (Box 16, Folder 303)
        "Flash/45 advance/Leopoldville 8..."
        "In the night the wire room..."
        "The rhymes lost their shimmer..."
        "We troymed in the delirium..."
        "We were reporters in the huge..."
        "bulletin/enas 37/o8171/Shangai..."
        "We were drunken with many words..."
        "The new language came with..."
        "and horizontal words..."
        "I was always homesick..."
        "What was the dream that always..."
        "Les amis d'enfance me saluèrent..."
        "Un iceberg se titana devant nous..."
        "Nous appretions à débarquer..."
        "In this tortured Europe..."
        "that fetching girl undid herself..."
        "Fatigued I came home..."
        "Dans les longues randonnées..."
        "Nous revions la nouvelle langue..."
        "We were the migrant men..."
        "quote We airwaved the flunties..."
        "Unfear was been stop unfright..."
        "That day we did not go to work..."
        "ALONE/IR/(11.49 PEEYEM: I have..."
        "We came from many lands we spoke..."
        "Bulletin/o8171/Zurich Quote..."
        "Epilogue: what are these sounds in my
        inner world..."
      - Section Q (Box 16, Folder 304)
        "Le chagrin du monde entre..."
        "Les mots-drames flambent..."
        "Nous battions contre les portes..."
        "I remembered straddling..."
        "Nos mots jouaient au carnaval..."
        "Trees of life grew spring..."
        "We are lost in the visceral..."
        "glostareen sulka astorrim alunt..."
        "The city was asleep and we were..."
        "We remember the walks..."
        "O City of metamorphoses..."
        "I wandered alone..."
        "Dans un crépuscule en delire..."
        GARGOYLES IN THE WAR
        I. "We slowly ascended..."
        II. "What was the sickness..."
        III. "We saw Oonla demon phantasma..."
        IV. "And there was Onaro oh Monster..."
        "We were stunned in the rainhour..."
        "We roamed about and came upon..."
        "Baal/L'homme solitaire guerroie..."
        "Je m'endormis sur un gratteciel..."
        "Les machines sont délirantes..."
        "Les années printannières..."
        "Walk around an hour: The air..."
        "Ete messin: La vallée brule..."
        "Homage to romanticism: My last..."
        "Nous attendions l'ile..."
        "Les algues se cramponnaient..."
        "The torried heat sickered down..."
        "The syllables of the new..."
        "I remembered in the titanic city..."
        "Our words were striated with..."
        "The grey ships were lying in..."
        "We walked through the abyssal..."
        "Unfear has been stop unfright..."
        "His memory walked again through..."
        "Nun wunderspricht die nacht von..."
      - Section R - Frankfurt Lobstershift (Box 16, Folder 305)
        "Summernight crashfalls..."
        "We were laired in the primitive..."
        "Munich Lobstershift: We are..."
      - Section S - Un News Room
        "Coulirant ou tricalta incantatio..."
        "Les vetements des métaphores..."
        "Nous revassons dans la nuit..."
        "Nebulasol shines over us..."
        "The illerhood berooned the lide..."
      - Section T - News from Germany (Box 16, Folder 306)
        Prologue
        Lament
        Ete Messin
        Proem
        Ode an die Reporter
        Reports of Solitude
        "We were lonely nomads..."
        "We saw the rivers of the world..."
        "We were in the servitude..."
        "We worked in the captured city..."
        "Washington: Seit Tagen fliegen..."
        "La grammaire était ravagée..."
        "Incendiary thoroughfare of metal..."
        "We sat around the little stove..."
        "The rockets went off with..."
        "The lobster shift creaked through..."
        "That day we saw violets growing..."
        "We watched the artillery battle..."
        "Spring gleamed over the shattered..."
        "Oh deep symbol of time we stood..."
        "One night we heard the crashgrunt..."
        "Old Hollands the printer we found..."
        "The bleek winter hours creaked..."
        "Lange tieftraumschliefen wir im..."
        "A broken piano moaned down..."
        - News from Germany (Box 16, Folder 307)
          "Aus kindheitstagen kamen die laute..."
          "The ghost of a dreamer wandered..."
          "For we are the new men..."
          "Gunthunder crattered across..."
          "Le temps restait toujours monacal..."
          "I seek your face..."
          "We waited for fireroar..."
        - Reports of Fear
          "Nous étions dans les calles..."
        - Reports of the Nox
          "Major Jim Chesnut said gosh..."
          "Tous les mots du foyer étaient..."
          "Nous traversions frontière..."
        - Reports of Migrations
        - Reports of Antithesis
          "We were tired and the wire room..."
          "LONDON NEWS-SHEET (1590)..."
        - Reports of Planets
        - Reports of Angels
          "The rain-dark day makes wandering..."
          "We said: We are in the abyssal..."
          "A new language came..."
          "What was that..." oh magical..."
          "The blackout enveloped..."
          "And Lumor said man has grown..."
          "The bells of Lyra rang..."
          "That fetching girl undid herself..."
          "Here's London here's London..."
          "Our words went into anguishnight..."
          "The Morse words glugged and..."
          "The Morse boys went into..."
          "Ok are you ready/Not yet wait..."
          "We thought of the war of..."
          "to some shleazy, titian-haired..."
          "We extractd dour words from..."
          "ALONA/IR/(11.49 PEEYEM..."
          - Lange tieftraumschliefen wir..." "Messager des Nations..." "We came from many lands we spoke..." "ALONE/IR/(11.49 PEEYEM..." "We remembered New York..." (Box 16, Folder 308)
          - "We were tired and the wire room..." "The bleak winter hours creaked..." "The rockets went off with..." "We sat around the little stove..." "Nous traversions la frontière..."
          - "The cortex of the age broke..." "The blackout enveloped..." "Nous avons marché..." "We said: We are in the abyssal..." "That day we saw violets growing..."
          - "For we are always homesick for..." "What is that dream that always..." "Les amis d'enfance me saluèrent..." "un iceberg se titana devant nous..." "Nous nous appretions..."